<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-02-02T21:55:46+00:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Voight Lab</title><subtitle>An engaging 1-3 sentence description of your lab.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Consortium-Level Activties</title><link href="/2024/01/11/Consortia.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Consortium-Level Activties" /><published>2024-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-02T21:55:00+00:00</updated><id>/2024/01/11/Consortia</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2024/01/11/Consortia.html"><![CDATA[<div class="button-wrapper">
    <a class="button" href="/publications" data-style="" aria-label="button">
      
      
        <span>Links to Pubs:</span>
      
    </a>
  </div>

<div class="tags" data-link="/publications">
    
      <a href="/publications?search=&quot;tag: PanKbase&quot;" class="tag" data-tooltip="Show items with the tag &quot;PanKbase&quot;">
        PanKbase
      </a>
    
      <a href="/publications?search=&quot;tag: T2D-GGI&quot;" class="tag" data-tooltip="Show items with the tag &quot;T2D-GGI&quot;">
        T2D-GGI
      </a>
    
      <a href="/publications?search=&quot;tag: T2D-AMP-CMD&quot;" class="tag" data-tooltip="Show items with the tag &quot;T2D-AMP-CMD&quot;">
        T2D-AMP-CMD
      </a>
    
      <a href="/publications?search=&quot;tag: MVP&quot;" class="tag" data-tooltip="Show items with the tag &quot;MVP&quot;">
        MVP
      </a>
    
  </div>

<!-- section break -->
<!--
  background: ;
  dark: ;
  size: ;
-->

<div class="button-wrapper">
    <a class="button" href="/2024/01/11/Consortia#T2D-GGI" data-style="" aria-label="button">
      
      
        <span>T2D-GGI</span>
      
    </a>
  </div>

<div class="button-wrapper">
    <a class="button" href="/2024/01/11/Consortia#MVP" data-style="" aria-label="button">
      
      
        <span>MVP</span>
      
    </a>
  </div>

<div class="button-wrapper">
    <a class="button" href="/2024/01/11/Consortia#T2D-AMP-CMD" data-style="" aria-label="button">
      
      
        <span>T2D-AMP-CMD</span>
      
    </a>
  </div>

<div class="button-wrapper">
    <a class="button" href="/2024/01/11/Consortia#PanKbase" data-style="" aria-label="button">
      
      
        <span>PanKbase</span>
      
    </a>
  </div>

<!-- section break -->
<!--
  background: ;
  dark: ;
  size: ;
-->

<p><a id="T2D-GGI"></a></p>

<h2 id="the-type-2-diabetes-global-genomics-initiative-t2d-ggi">The Type 2 Diabetes Global Genomics Initiative (T2D-GGI)</h2>
<p>I have a long-standing commitment to mapping genetic susceptibility loci for type 2 diabetes (T2D). I was part of the first groups to perform GWAS successfully – our efforts there to bring together data initially to make statistically robust (and replicated) observations formed the basis of genome-wide meta-analyses that we currently enjoy conventionally today. For T2D, I was part of <a href="https://diagram-consortium.org/">DIAGRAM</a>, the first consortium for meta-analysis of T2D data. Today, with long-standing colleagues (Andrew Morris and Ele Zeggini), I co-lead the Type 2 Diabetes Global Genomics Initiative (T2D-GGI), which carries the torch of that previous effort. Our initial effort has been to <a href="https://www.medrxiv.org/content/10.1101/2023.03.31.23287839v1">assemble &gt;2.5M participants for the largest multi-ancestry GWAS of T2D to date</a>. Ongoing efforts of that group include use of those data to connect to gene and physiology (through statistical colocalization), refinement and characterization of genetic subtypes of diabetes through clustering methods, causal inference studies via Mendelian randomization, or signal fine-mapping. We are a collaborative, inclusive group and projects that utilize data in this area can give trainees exposure to and experience with fantastically effective large-scale multi-institutional consortium work, which is increasingly typical in human genomics activities.</p>

<div class="button-wrapper">
    <a class="button" href="/2024/01/11/Consortia" data-style="" aria-label="button">
      
      
        <span>Back to Top</span>
      
    </a>
  </div>

<!-- section break -->
<!--
  background: ;
  dark: ;
  size: ;
-->

<p><a id="MVP"></a></p>

<h2 id="the-va-million-veteran-program">The VA Million Veteran Program</h2>
<p>The VA’s Million Veteran Program (MVP) is a national research program looking at how genes, lifestyle, military experiences, and exposures affect health and wellness in Veterans. Since launching in 2011, 1 million Veterans have joined MVP. It is the largest research effort at VA to improve health care for Veterans and one of the largest research programs in the world studying genes and health. I have a without compensation (WOC) appointment at the local VA here in Philadelphia (CMC), connected to Cardiometabolic Trait and Disease projects funded projects (to Kyong-Mi Chang at Penn, and Phil Tsao, Stanford) as well as projects related to CVD/PAD (to Scott Damrauer). My primary contribution focused around genetic discovery and analysis for T2D, liver disease, and CVD. This resource is particularly exciting to me with numerous opportunities for projects and productive scholarship, as its highly diverse representation at large sample size in a single repository make it ideal for complex trait genetic and population genetic discovery, characterization of genetic architecture, but also for causal inference using Mendelian randomization approaches that also have the opportunity to work at the individual level. To give one example of the potential of this: I was fortunate to join colleagues nation wide, to report <a href="https://www.medrxiv.org/content/10.1101/2023.06.28.23291975v1">a genome-wide, Phenome-wide association study across MVP participants</a>. The scope and volume of computation require to complete this project require collaborations with the DOE and supercomputer access with modified, efficient implementations of analysis tools, leading to new collaborations and inference at scale that has hitherto not been reported.</p>

<div class="button-wrapper">
    <a class="button" href="/2024/01/11/Consortia" data-style="" aria-label="button">
      
      
        <span>Back to Top</span>
      
    </a>
  </div>

<!-- section break -->
<!--
  background: ;
  dark: ;
  size: ;
-->

<p><a id="T2D-AMP-CMD"></a></p>

<h2 id="the-type-2-diabetes---accelerating-medicines-partnership---common-metabolic-disease---functional-genomics-project-t2d-amp-cmd-fgp">The Type 2 Diabetes - Accelerating Medicines Partnership - Common Metabolic Disease - Functional Genomics Project (T2D AMP CMD FGP)</h2>
<p>Large-scale genome-wide association studies (GWAS) have lead to the rapid identification of hundreds of T2D-associated loci. However, the mechanism(s) through which most of these loci influence disease susceptibility remain poorly understood. An interdisciplinary team at Penn (including Pat Seale, Wenli Yang, Struan Grant, Klaus Kaestner, Dan Rader, and myself) brings together experts in population genetics, T2D GWAS, biostatistics, metabolic tissue biology, human cellular disease modeling and T2D pathophysiology to tackle this critical knowledge gap. In collaboration with our consortium partners, our goal is to provide the diabetes research community with a robust pipeline for mapping T2D GWAS variants to effector genes and target tissues, identify new genes and biological pathways that modulate susceptibility to T2D, and define gene regulatory networks relevant to T2D with the goal of uncovering therapeutic ‘entry
points’ for developing new treatments. My efforts in this consortium lead on genetic discovery and characterization, closely partnering with groups focused on prioritizing putative effector transcripts using QTL mapping data. We also collaborate locally with Penn investigators to help interpret genetics data and to priortize leads that merit functional follow-up studies.</p>

<div class="button-wrapper">
    <a class="button" href="/2024/01/11/Consortia" data-style="" aria-label="button">
      
      
        <span>Back to Top</span>
      
    </a>
  </div>

<!-- section break -->
<!--
  background: ;
  dark: ;
  size: ;
-->

<p><a id="PanKbase"></a></p>

<h2 id="pankbase-human-islet-research-network-hirn-pancreas-knowledgebase-program-pankbase">PanKbase: Human Islet Research Network (HIRN) Pancreas Knowledgebase Program (PanKbase)</h2>
<p>A wealth of data has been generated in human pancreas donors in initiatives supported by the Human Islet Research Network (HIRN) which can be used to address open questions in type 1 diabetes, yet these data are currently both underutilized and in formats inaccessible to many researchers which prohibits insights. To address this gap, the NIDDK has assembled two groups of highly accomplished researchers to create a pancreatic knowledge base - <em>PanKbase</em> - which leverages expertise in computational biology and data science, type 1 diabetes, islet biology, knowledge base engineering, and engagement and outreach. This is an incredibly new collaboration (as of Feb 2024); I expect more details to emerge about the goals, objectives, and deliverables for the project as the group organized and gets situated.</p>

<div class="button-wrapper">
    <a class="button" href="/2024/01/11/Consortia" data-style="" aria-label="button">
      
      
        <span>Back to Top</span>
      
    </a>
  </div>]]></content><author><name>Ben Voight</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Links to Pubs: PanKbase T2D-GGI T2D-AMP-CMD MVP]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Aspirational Projects</title><link href="/2024/01/11/Projects-Aspirational.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Aspirational Projects" /><published>2024-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-02T21:55:00+00:00</updated><id>/2024/01/11/Projects-Aspirational</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2024/01/11/Projects-Aspirational.html"><![CDATA[<div class="button-wrapper">
    <a class="button" href="/publications" data-style="" aria-label="button">
      
      
        <span>Links to Pubs:</span>
      
    </a>
  </div>

<div class="tags" data-link="/publications">
    
      <a href="/publications?search=&quot;tag: Spiders&quot;" class="tag" data-tooltip="Show items with the tag &quot;Spiders&quot;">
        Spiders
      </a>
    
      <a href="/publications?search=&quot;tag: Docking&quot;" class="tag" data-tooltip="Show items with the tag &quot;Docking&quot;">
        Docking
      </a>
    
  </div>

<!-- section break -->
<!--
  background: ;
  dark: ;
  size: ;
-->

<div class="button-wrapper">
    <a class="button" href="/2024/01/11/Projects-Aspirational#Spiders" data-style="" aria-label="button">
      
      
        <span>Spiders</span>
      
    </a>
  </div>

<div class="button-wrapper">
    <a class="button" href="/2024/01/11/Projects-Aspirational#Docking" data-style="" aria-label="button">
      
      
        <span>Docking</span>
      
    </a>
  </div>

<!-- section break -->
<!--
  background: ;
  dark: ;
  size: ;
-->

<p><a id="Spiders"></a></p>

<h2 id="spider-genomics">Spider Genomics</h2>

<p>Spiders are an amazing species, most notably for producing biomaterials that have some of the most unique and diverse biophysical properties of materials found in nature. Our previous work focused on the genomic assembly and silk-gene characterization of two species of spiders: the Golden-Orb weaver <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trichonephila_clavipes"><em>Trichonephila clavipes</em></a>, one of the most well-studies arachnids for silk biology, and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Darwin%27s_bark_spider"><em>Caerostris darwini</em></a>, a species native to Madagascar infamous for its extremely tough draglines used in the webs that it builds over riverways there for predation.</p>

<p>We remain interested in characterizing these (and other) related spider species, as sequencing technologies develop and advance. For example, some project directions could include creating a more ‘complete’ Telomere-to-Telomere genome, collecting population genetic data to characterize demographic history, variation in mutation rates, and detecting signature of natural selection, or using advances sequencing technologies to characterize transcript expression in silk glands at single-cell and/or at spatial resolution.</p>

<div class="cols" style="--cols: 2">
  
    
    <div>
<figure class="figure">
  <a class="figure-image" aria-label="Golden Orb Weaver Spiderlings in the lab!">
    <img src="/images/spiderling01.jpg" style="
        width: auto;
        max-height: unset;
      " alt="Golden Orb Weaver Spiderlings in the lab!" loading="lazy" onerror="this.src = '/images/fallback.svg'; this.onerror = null;" />
  </a>
  
    <figcaption class="figure-caption">
      Golden Orb Weaver Spiderlings in the lab!

    </figcaption>
  
</figure>

</div>
  
    
    <div>
<iframe width="315" height="480" src="https://youtube.com/embed/v74bsD6lRoo" title="Spiderlings on the Lam!" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; clipboard-write; encrypted-media;
gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

</div>
  
</div>

<div class="button-wrapper">
    <a class="button" href="/2024/01/11/Projects-Aspirational" data-style="" aria-label="button">
      
      
        <span>Back to Top</span>
      
    </a>
  </div>

<!-- section break -->
<!--
  background: ;
  dark: ;
  size: ;
-->

<p><a id="Docking"></a></p>

<h2 id="computational-prediction-of-molecular-docking">Computational Prediction of Molecular Docking</h2>

<p>A great deal of effort in human genetics is focused on solving the “variant-to-gene” mapping problem; namely, identifying what gene at a given locus is causal for the phenotype/disease that is associated with regional variation. However, once a leading gene has been identified and proven to be implicated in disease beyond a reasonable doubt (typically with functional data from cell or animal model systems data), it is natural to ask if the protein product of that gene can be perturbed with a small molecule to obtain a therapeutic effect. While this direction of experimental effort is often considered an affair for the private sector, development of ‘tool’ small molecules, precursors for true therapeutics that demonstrate potential effect, is still a risky proposition. Moreover, biochemical perturbation of gene targets that are consistent with the observed human genetics phenotypic data provides another line of evidence for gene relevance, even if the target is not fully actionable.</p>

<p>While a substantial computational task, if sufficiently high-resolution protein structures for a target exists, there are tools that can model the proclivity of a small molecule to ‘dock’ with the surface of that structure. We are interested in identifying targets of opportunity, namely, for cardiometabolic traits of lab interest where we have implicated a gene beyond reasonable doubt, to determine which (if any) of those targets are amenable to computational docking experiments. Screening millions of compounds takes computational time, so we are also interested in developing computationally efficient pipelines to take this task on at scale.</p>

<div class="button-wrapper">
    <a class="button" href="/2024/01/11/Projects-Aspirational" data-style="" aria-label="button">
      
      
        <span>Back to Top</span>
      
    </a>
  </div>]]></content><author><name>Ben Voight</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Links to Pubs: Spiders Docking]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Projects in Complex Trait Genetics</title><link href="/2024/01/11/Projects-Complex-Traits.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Projects in Complex Trait Genetics" /><published>2024-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-02T21:55:00+00:00</updated><id>/2024/01/11/Projects-Complex-Traits</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2024/01/11/Projects-Complex-Traits.html"><![CDATA[<div class="button-wrapper">
    <a class="button" href="/publications" data-style="" aria-label="button">
      
      
        <span>Links to Pubs:</span>
      
    </a>
  </div>

<div class="tags" data-link="/publications">
    
      <a href="/publications?search=&quot;tag: Complex Traits&quot;" class="tag" data-tooltip="Show items with the tag &quot;Complex Traits&quot;">
        Complex Traits
      </a>
    
      <a href="/publications?search=&quot;tag: T2D&quot;" class="tag" data-tooltip="Show items with the tag &quot;T2D&quot;">
        T2D
      </a>
    
      <a href="/publications?search=&quot;tag: MASLD&quot;" class="tag" data-tooltip="Show items with the tag &quot;MASLD&quot;">
        MASLD
      </a>
    
      <a href="/publications?search=&quot;tag: CAD/CVD&quot;" class="tag" data-tooltip="Show items with the tag &quot;CAD/CVD&quot;">
        CAD/CVD
      </a>
    
      <a href="/publications?search=&quot;tag: QTL Mapping&quot;" class="tag" data-tooltip="Show items with the tag &quot;QTL Mapping&quot;">
        QTL Mapping
      </a>
    
  </div>

<!-- section break -->
<!--
  background: ;
  dark: ;
  size: ;
-->

<div class="button-wrapper">
    <a class="button" href="/2024/01/11/Projects-Complex-Traits#T2D" data-style="" aria-label="button">
      
      
        <span>T2D</span>
      
    </a>
  </div>

<div class="button-wrapper">
    <a class="button" href="/2024/01/11/Projects-Complex-Traits#MASLD" data-style="" aria-label="button">
      
      
        <span>MASLD</span>
      
    </a>
  </div>

<div class="button-wrapper">
    <a class="button" href="/2024/01/11/Projects-Complex-Traits#QTL-Mapping" data-style="" aria-label="button">
      
      
        <span>QTL Mapping</span>
      
    </a>
  </div>

<div class="button-wrapper">
    <a class="button" href="/2024/01/11/Projects-Complex-Traits#Collabs" data-style="" aria-label="button">
      
      
        <span>Additional Collaborations</span>
      
    </a>
  </div>

<!-- section break -->
<!--
  background: ;
  dark: ;
  size: ;
-->

<p><a id="T2D"></a></p>

<h2 id="discovery-and-analysis-type-2-diabetes-and-its-complications">Discovery and Analysis: Type-2 Diabetes and its Complications</h2>
<p>I have a longstanding interest in dissection of the genetic basis of type 2 diabetes (T2D). A great deal of progress has been made in characterizing the basis of the disease, in no small part to the advent of genome-wide association studies (GWAS) and the scale to which data can be collected. My efforts over my career thusfar has contributed to data collection and analysis that has resulted in the discovery of hundreds of associated loci to date. While work continues to expand discovery of new loci for the disease, expanding especially towards characterization of genetic liability across diverse cohorts, a great deal of work still remains “post” genome-wide association study. My fundamental drive is to identify genes and pathways that are therapeutically actionable, to expand the collection of treatments available, perhaps personally tailored to the sub-structure of genetic risk to T2D that an individual might carry. I believe genomics data collected in humans is central to that effort: identifying relevant leads, the therapeutic direction of effect, the ‘horsepower’ of specific human genetic targets, and so forth. As such, there are a range of GWAS and post-GWAS activities that are of active interest in the lab, with project invariably collaborative and large-scale with the <a href="Consortia#T2D-GGI">T2D-GGI</a> and <a href="Consortia#MVP">MVP</a> consortia. To enumerate a couple of areas interest:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Locus Discovery</strong>. Our most recent work has reported the assembly &gt;2.5M participants for the largest multi-ancestry GWAS of T2D to date, which lead to 145 newly loci for disease and bring the number of distinct loci to 611 and signals to 1289. However, this still did not bring the complete collection of data to bear. Ongoing data collection continues with AllofUs, MVP, and potentially bringing in cohorts to cover population groups that were not as well represented in this new effort as would have been desired (e.g., from South Asia).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Signal Fine Mapping</strong>. Mapping causal variants is directly relevant to causal gene identification, understanding mechanisms, and disease progression. Signal fine mapping is the appropriate statistical method to identify multiple, statistically independent signals associated, and is important as it: (i) extends the heritability explained by genetics, allowing us to deduce the relevance of causal variants shared across – but also potentially unique to – ancestry groups, (ii) allows us to connect association signals to additional metabolic and progression traits directly, and (iii) provides additional leads to connect to a putative causal nearby gene.
In our initial efforts for T2D-GGI, we applied fairly coarse (heuristic, but not quantitative) approach to capture putatively independent signals of association at each distinct T2D-associated locus. However, the toolkit of available approaches and data sets to deeply characterize the full spectrum of allelic heterogeneity comprehensively have never been better. I am particularly interested in application of these tools for T2D-GGI, to bring together true ‘in sample’ LD reference panels for large biobanks with summary data they contributed to meta-analysis to attack this problem.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Causal inference</strong>. Within the T2D-GGI, collaborations are ongoing to use the framework of Mendelian randomization (MR), QTL data, and multi-ancestry information to triangulate on variants and their predicted effects on nearby genes, to identify direction of effects and ‘horsepower’ of given perturbations of that gene to risk to T2D that might be expected. In addition, I am also interested in understanding non-linear effects of established causal risk factors and lifestyle factors in the context of T2D genetic liability. These questions can be addressed with the framework of MR, but require individual level data - which is available in MVP. Use of these data potentially further facilitates exploration of the role of causal risk factors for T2D across diversity ancestries, and to relate those risk factors potentially to risk of complications of T2D.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Colocalizaton: Variant-to-Gene Mapping and multi-trait physiology</strong>. It is highly desirable to connect non-coding variants – the lion’s share of tagged association at T2D risk loci – with a cognate, putatively relevant gene <em>in cis</em>. This can be achieved computationally through varaint-to-gene mapping approaches, e.g. using variation associated with change in transcript abundance (eQTLs) in relevant tissues or cell types (e.g., beta-cells of pancreatic islets). We are interested in attacking the variant-to-gene mapping problem generally, through analysis of existing data as well as generating new QTL data sets for this purpose - but also in the context of credible sets identified from signal fine-mapping efforts. In addition, we are also interested in attaching the complete spectrum of physiologic associations at each signal of association. We are interested in this approach, to (i) help understand the traits that might be expected to be perturbed (which may be beneficial or antagonistic to therapeutic indications), (ii) as a vehicle to help characterize pleiotropy generally in the genome, and (iii) to potentially obtain leads for the potential tissue or cell type of action that may be physiologically implicated at the associated signal.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Genetic Sub-Typing via Trait Clustering</strong>. In our recent work, and consistent with reports from others, it is possible to group T2D signals by cardiometabolic and anthropometric trait associations at those loci. These clusters appear to map onto to distinctive functional genomic and tissue groupings, e.g., beta-cell biology vs. adipose / obesity biology. In our paper, we demonstrated initial evidence that these sub-types may also diffferent associate with risk of T2D complications, though clearly more work to fuel stratification are necessary. In additional collaborative work within the T2D-GGI, we are exploring and contrasting different approaches to clustering, and are interested in evaluating new approaches to clustering fueled by additional data or new ways to approach the problem (e.g., colocalization or fine-mapping). The objective is potentially to develop and identify types that predict downstream complications (e.g., CAD, Kidney disease, retinopathy, etc.), which could potentially be transformative if successful.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<div class="button-wrapper">
    <a class="button" href="/2024/01/11/Projects-Complex-Traits" data-style="" aria-label="button">
      
      
        <span>Back to Top</span>
      
    </a>
  </div>

<!-- section break -->
<!--
  background: ;
  dark: ;
  size: ;
-->

<p><a id="MASLD"></a></p>

<h2 id="discovery-and-analysis-metabolic-associated-steatotic-liver-disease-and-its-progression">Discovery and Analysis: Metabolic-associated steatotic liver disease and its Progression</h2>
<p>Through involvement with MVP, I have recently become interested in dissecting the genetic basis of metabolic-associated steatotic liver disease (MASLD, previously referred to as NAFLD) and its progression. Our efforts involve not just locus discovery for the trait (or proxy) and progression phenotypes, but also post-GWAS analyses, and is a collaborative activity with many investigators at Penn and the VA, including Kyong-Mi Chang and Marijana Vujkovic, among many others.</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Locus Discovery</strong>. Following along <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41588-022-01078-z">our previously work</a>, efforts continue to map new susceptibility loci for the disease, or for related traits like liver cancer or cirrhosis. As data sets continue to grow, we are intrested in aggregating them for novel discovery as well as for down-stream analyses.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Signal fine mapping</strong>. Mapping causal variants is directly relevant to causal gene identification, understanding mechanisms, and disease progression. Signal fine mapping is the appropriate statistical method to identify multiple, statistically independent signals associated with disease. These allow us to extend heritability explained as well as find new targets for variant-to-gene mapping. As with T2D, I am particularly interested in application of novel tools and applications in MVP to deeply characterize the full spectrum of allelic heterogeneity comprehensively have never been better. The collection of liver disease and progression traits are opportune target for these efforts.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Multi-Trait mapping</strong>. MASLD by new definition carries with it at least one cardiometabolic trait association. I am interested in characterizing the trait physiology perturbed at MASLD and progression traits, identifying loci that are associated with lean MASLD, and performing multi-trait GWAS to expand the catalog of relevant associations that could be targets for functional studies beyond our primary scan.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Functional validation of MASLD Loci in the Zebrafish model system</strong>. Of established MASLD associations, a few transcripts identified through GWAS have been assigned causality for relevant phenotypic traits, such as liver fat, injury, or fibrosis/cirrhosis. These transcripts harbor variants with positive or negative risk associations that act through loss- and gain-of-function mechanisms in either hepatocytes or communicating cell types (immune). But like other complex diseases, many of the leading variants associated with MASLD are non-coding, which do not demarcate a clear candidate gene. While computational approaches can narrow down the list of potential candidates to reduce the number of genes in the list, candidate genes nominated in this way still require functional validation to demonstrate a phenotypic effect, direction of effect, and underlying mechanisms. Because we have dozens of MASLD candidate genes to evaluate, we need <em>in vivo</em> model system that facilitates tractable throughput, is scalable, and yet retains phenotypic depth and relevance. As such, we are embarked to build a collaboration with den Hoed Lab (Uppsala) to use zebrafish as a model system for validation. Zebrafish have a well-annotated genome with orthologues of at least 71% of human genes, or 82% of human disease-associated genes. Our results so far show strong directional consistency in effects on liver fat across zebrafish larvae and humans or mice for genes previously implicated through pLOF variants.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<div class="button-wrapper">
    <a class="button" href="/2024/01/11/Projects-Complex-Traits" data-style="" aria-label="button">
      
      
        <span>Back to Top</span>
      
    </a>
  </div>

<!-- section break -->
<!--
  background: ;
  dark: ;
  size: ;
-->

<p><a id="QTL-Mapping"></a></p>

<h2 id="quantitative-trait-locus-mapping-activities">Quantitative Trait Locus Mapping Activities</h2>
<p>We have recently expanded our interest and expertise in performing genetic mapping of molecular phenotypes, i.e., quantitative trait locus (QTL) discovery. Previously, we have performed scans in cell models for transcript abundance (eQTLs) or proportion of alternative spliced isoforms (sQTLs), and collaborate with local investigators to study primary tissues, including kidney (with Katalin Susztak). More recently, we are involved in several projects which utilize primary tissue in bulk and at single cell resolution, as well as expanding to chromatin accessibility (caQTL) mapping. Active projects include:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Single-cell eQTL and caQTL mapping for islet-cell types</strong>. In collaboration with Gaulton Lab (UCSD) and Grant Lab (Penn/CHOP), led by shared graduate student (Mary Ann Weidekamp), we are using single-cell data generated by the Human Pancreas Analysis Program which is collecting multi-omic readouts of pancreatic tissue obtained from deceased donors. These data include scRNA-Seq but also scATAC-Seq, and more recently, multiome RNA/ATAC-seq readouts. Our initial focus has been on mapping eQTLs in alpha, beta, and delta-cell populations, as well as additional cell types also captured in this experiment (e.g. acinar cells).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>QTL mapping of B/T cells in pediatric cohort</strong>. In collaboration with Romberg Lab (CHOP), we are engaged in eQTL mapping in matched immune cell types (T cell, B cell) obtained from tonsil tissues extracted from pediatric cohorts, under baseline and stimulated conditions. These data are particularly novel, as they characterize immune cell populations from within a tissue context (not circulating in Blood, i.e. PBMCs), and derived from a pediatric cohort (age &lt;18). Our initial efforts in &gt;100 subjects have mapped ~14,000 eGenes in basal and stimulated states, including &gt;1,700 not previously reported in either large scale data sets (i.e., GTEx or eQTLGen) nor from catalogs of eQTLs from immune cell type data obtainde from PBMCs (i.e., the DICE consortium).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>caQTL mapping in Bulk Liver</strong>. Lead by a graduate student (Bradon Wenz) during his time working with Casey Brown, we are focused on the analysis of ~180 primary bulk liver samples that he profiled using chromatin accessibility mapping via ATAC-Seq. The result is a massive map of regions of accessible chromatin in bulk liver tissue as well as a catalog of caQTLs. We are working together to finalize the analyses for these data.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<div class="button-wrapper">
    <a class="button" href="/2024/01/11/Projects-Complex-Traits" data-style="" aria-label="button">
      
      
        <span>Back to Top</span>
      
    </a>
  </div>

<!-- section break -->
<!--
  background: ;
  dark: ;
  size: ;
-->

<p><a id="Collabs"></a></p>

<h2 id="additional-collaborative-projects">Additional Collaborative Projects</h2>
<p>We also have a number of ongoing projects that generally involve collaborations or shared graduate students with another lab with complementary expertise our lab:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Fine-mapping and functional validation in Bone-mineral Density</strong>. Genetic factors strongly influence bone mineral density (BMD) and osteoporosis risk over time. To date, genome-wide association studies (GWAS) have discovered over 1,100 independent BMD signals; however, the causal variant(s) and respective effector gene(s) for the majority of these loci remain unknown. In collaboration with the Grant Lab, we <a href="https://genomebiology.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s13059-020-02207-9">previously published the results</a> of a 3D genomics-based ‘variant-to-gene’ mapping method for BMD loci based on ATAC-seq, RNA-seq, and chromatin confirmation capture data from hMSC-derived osteoblasts. Led by graduate student (Mitch Conery) co-advised by Struan and myself, we are applying this approach, which links putative causal variants in open chromatin to candidate effector genes via chromatin interactions with open promoters, to a dataset derived from the human fetal osteoblast 1.19 cell line (hFOB). For validation of both sets of findings at scale, we conducted a CRISPRi screen in hFOBs differentiated for five days. In addition, Mitch is performing multi-trait signal fine-mapping for these signals across a range of related traits, to inform further prioritization efforts and potentially link BMD signals to novel biological and physiological mechanisms.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Genome-wide, phenome-wide Association studies in MVP</strong>. I was fortunate to join colleagues nation wide, to report <a href="https://www.medrxiv.org/content/10.1101/2023.06.28.23291975v1">a genome-wide, Phenome-wide association study across MVP participants</a>. The scope and volume of computation require to complete this project require collaborations with the DOE and supercomputer access with modified, efficient implementations of analysis tools, leading to new collaborations and inference at scale that has hitherto not been reported. There, across &gt;2,000 traits in &gt;630K MVP participants, we reported &gt;38,000 independent variants associated with 1 or more traits, performed fine-mapping which resulted in 6,318 singals from 613 traits to single-variant resolution. Future work extends in this vein to involve X-Chromosome analysis and expanded fine-mapping using multi-ancestry aware tools like SuSiEx, meSuSiE, mJAM, or flashfm.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<div class="button-wrapper">
    <a class="button" href="/2024/01/11/Projects-Complex-Traits" data-style="" aria-label="button">
      
      
        <span>Back to Top</span>
      
    </a>
  </div>]]></content><author><name>Ben Voight</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Links to Pubs: Complex Traits T2D MASLD CAD/CVD QTL Mapping]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Projects in Mendelian Randomization</title><link href="/2024/01/11/Projects-MR.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Projects in Mendelian Randomization" /><published>2024-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-02T21:55:00+00:00</updated><id>/2024/01/11/Projects-MR</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2024/01/11/Projects-MR.html"><![CDATA[<div class="button-wrapper">
    <a class="button" href="/publications" data-style="" aria-label="button">
      
      
        <span>Links to Pubs:</span>
      
    </a>
  </div>

<div class="tags" data-link="/publications">
    
      <a href="/publications?search=&quot;tag: Mendelian Randomization&quot;" class="tag" data-tooltip="Show items with the tag &quot;Mendelian Randomization&quot;">
        Mendelian Randomization
      </a>
    
  </div>

<!-- section break -->
<!--
  background: ;
  dark: ;
  size: ;
-->

<div class="button-wrapper">
    <a class="button" href="/2024/01/11/Projects-MR#Analysis" data-style="" aria-label="button">
      
      
        <span>MR Analysis</span>
      
    </a>
  </div>

<div class="button-wrapper">
    <a class="button" href="/2024/01/11/Projects-MR#Methods" data-style="" aria-label="button">
      
      
        <span>MR Methods</span>
      
    </a>
  </div>

<!-- section break -->
<!--
  background: ;
  dark: ;
  size: ;
-->

<h2 id="overview">Overview</h2>
<p>Causal inference is one of the most challenging problems in biology and medicine, requiring multiple lines of evidence supported by model systems, pharmacology, and genetics to demonstrate convincingly. Under specific assumptions, it is possible to use human genetic variation as an instrumental variable to estimate the causal effect of an exposure on an outcome. For example, loss-of-function variation in <em>PCSK9</em> lowers LDL cholesterol (LDL-C) and susceptibility to heart disease, consistent with the fact that elevated LDL-C is a causal risk factor for heart attack. There is much nuance here, with advances in new methods, understanding the testable (and untestable) assumptions of the model, kits of tools that make application very straight forward – a complete didact on this subject is well beyond the purpose of this short overview. For those who are interested, I strongly recommend picking up a recently published MR Primer:</p>

<div class="citation">
  
    <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s43586-021-00092-5" class="citation-image" aria-label="Mendelian randomization">
      <img src="" alt="Mendelian randomization" loading="lazy" onerror="this.src = '/images/fallback.svg'; this.onerror = null;" />
    </a>
  

  <div class="citation-text">
    
    

    <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s43586-021-00092-5" class="citation-title">
      Mendelian randomization
    </a>

    <div class="citation-authors" data-tooltip="Sanderson E, Glymour MM, Holmes MV, Kang H, Morrison J, Munafò MR, Palmer T, Schooling CM, Wallace C, Zhao Q, Smith GD " tabindex="0">
      Sanderson E,  Glymour MM,  Holmes MV,  Kang H,  Morrison J, ...,  Palmer T,  Schooling CM,  Wallace C,  Zhao Q,  Smith GD
    </div>

    <div class="citation-details">
      Nature Reviews Methods Primers
      &nbsp; · &nbsp;
      10 Feb 2022
      &nbsp; · &nbsp;
      doi.org/10.1038/s43586-021-00092-5
    </div>

    
      

      

      
    
  </div>
</div>

<p><a id="Analysis"></a></p>

<h2 id="mendelian-randomization-analyses">Mendelian Randomization Analyses</h2>
<p>We are generally interested in novel relationship discovery as well as clarifying previously observed exposure-outcome relationships, particularly (but not exclusive to) the cardiometabolic trait space. For example, we have explored the role of smoking and body mass index (BMI) on T2D risk, serum urate on CAD/T2D, and BMI and Waist-Hip ratio (WHR) on blood traits. Ongoing / active projects include:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><em>Nutrition / dietary exposure on cardiometabolic traits/disease</em>. Dietary preference is conventionally thought of as an environmental risk factor, but previous studies have elucidated a significant (but small) heritable component to this collection of traits. This facilitates MR experiments to understand what, if any, role this ‘environmental’ exposure has on T2D, CVD, or related causal traits. A leading hypothesis is that risk from dietary preference to outcome is mediated through anthropometric factors like adiposity. This work is led by Mia Lee (PGG graduate student) in the lab.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><em>Phenome-wide MR; considerations for diverse ancestry analysis</em>.  In collaboration with Drs. Venexia Walker and Tom Gaunt (Univ. of Bristol, UK) and Dr. Scott Damrauer (Penn), we are engaged in a broad stroke, all-by-all MR experiment (i.e., hundreds of exposure-outcome pairings) via summary data from MVP and the UKBB. This will provide a deep, well powered resource for discovery, but will explore the role and extent of biases that must be contended with in the case of ancestry mismatching.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><em>Collaborative activities with T2D-GGI</em>. Collaborating within the T2D-GGI, we are engaged in the latest GWAS for T2D and QTL data through which we can ‘drug target’ via QTLs. The goal with this approach is to identify potential leads and directions of effect for changes in molecular phenotype (e.g., expression) with a target gene, to make an educated guess at the predicted effect that would be therapeutic. In addition, work is underway which seeks to relate our previously defined genetic clusters to T2D comorbidities (e.g., retinopathy, stroke, etc.) through the MR framework.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>Generally, we are open to different types of analysis projects that are along the lines of specific targeted questions!</p>

<div class="button-wrapper">
    <a class="button" href="/2024/01/11/Projects-MR" data-style="" aria-label="button">
      
      
        <span>Back to Top</span>
      
    </a>
  </div>

<!-- section break -->
<!--
  background: ;
  dark: ;
  size: ;
-->

<p><a id="Methods"></a></p>

<h2 id="mendelian-randomization-methodology">Mendelian Randomization Methodology</h2>

<p>We are also interested in developing methods in MR studies. Previously, we have developed pipelines and a simulation engine to evaluate (empirically) MR under different models and assumptions.</p>

<p>Methods development for MR is a particular challenge, broadly because the field moves rapidly and there are a great many biostatistician/epidemiologists who have dedicated their entire operation to MR (and methods development). Where possible, we seek to bring in these latest methods into ongoing work. Occasionally, we identify methodologic “targets of opportunity” while working with Big Data sets or by pushing the envelope of human genomics studies. We have a couple of areas of interest in this space, primarily along the lines of instrument curation, and when considering large-scale data sets which derive from a plurality of ancestries. That said, my group is certainly open to other lines of inquiry, so interested parties should express their interest so that we can discuss further.</p>

<div class="button-wrapper">
    <a class="button" href="/2024/01/11/Projects-MR" data-style="" aria-label="button">
      
      
        <span>Back to Top</span>
      
    </a>
  </div>]]></content><author><name>Ben Voight</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Links to Pubs: Mendelian Randomization]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Projects in Population Genetics</title><link href="/2024/01/11/Projects-Pop-Gen.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Projects in Population Genetics" /><published>2024-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-02T21:55:00+00:00</updated><id>/2024/01/11/Projects-Pop-Gen</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2024/01/11/Projects-Pop-Gen.html"><![CDATA[<div class="button-wrapper">
    <a class="button" href="/publications" data-style="" aria-label="button">
      
      
        <span>Links to Pubs:</span>
      
    </a>
  </div>

<div class="tags" data-link="/publications">
    
      <a href="/publications?search=&quot;tag: Pop Gen&quot;" class="tag" data-tooltip="Show items with the tag &quot;Pop Gen&quot;">
        Pop Gen
      </a>
    
      <a href="/publications?search=&quot;tag: Mutation Rate&quot;" class="tag" data-tooltip="Show items with the tag &quot;Mutation Rate&quot;">
        Mutation Rate
      </a>
    
      <a href="/publications?search=&quot;tag: Selection&quot;" class="tag" data-tooltip="Show items with the tag &quot;Selection&quot;">
        Selection
      </a>
    
      <a href="/publications?search=&quot;tag: Baymer&quot;" class="tag" data-tooltip="Show items with the tag &quot;Baymer&quot;">
        Baymer
      </a>
    
      <a href="/publications?search=&quot;tag: Demography&quot;" class="tag" data-tooltip="Show items with the tag &quot;Demography&quot;">
        Demography
      </a>
    
  </div>

<!-- section break -->
<!--
  background: ;
  dark: ;
  size: ;
-->

<div class="button-wrapper">
    <a class="button" href="/2024/01/11/Projects-Pop-Gen#Mutation-Rate" data-style="" aria-label="button">
      
      
        <span>Mutation Rates</span>
      
    </a>
  </div>

<div class="button-wrapper">
    <a class="button" href="/2024/01/11/Projects-Pop-Gen#Selection" data-style="" aria-label="button">
      
      
        <span>Selection</span>
      
    </a>
  </div>

<div class="button-wrapper">
    <a class="button" href="/2024/01/11/Projects-Pop-Gen#Interface" data-style="" aria-label="button">
      
      
        <span>Interface of Pop-Gen/Complex Traits</span>
      
    </a>
  </div>

<!-- section break -->
<!--
  background: ;
  dark: ;
  size: ;
-->

<p><a id="Mutation-Rate"></a></p>

<h2 id="inference-of-mutation-rate-variation-across-genomes">Inference of Mutation Rate Variation across Genomes</h2>

<p>Mutation is one of the most important processes generating variation within and between species, and is a fundamental process underlying molecular evolution. My lab is generally interested in work to identify correlates of - and ways to ultimately explain - variation in where, what type, and how frequent different types of mutational events occur in genomes: polymorphisms, substitutions, <em>de novo</em> events, somatic mutations, etc. Ultimately, better models to explain variation in mutation rates across genomes can help interpret evidence for selection (e.g., functional constraint), timing and the pace of the molecular evolutionary clock, how the process of mutation has changes over time or may be different across populations or across the tree of life broadly. Moreover, better models may also ultimately help us to understand mechanism, i.e., what are the ultimately environmental and molecular drivers underlying the mutational process.</p>

<p>To date, our work has mainly focused on modeling variation in mutation rates using sequence context – the local nucleotides that flank a mutated site. For example, it is well known that the rate of C&gt;T transition mutations are substantially elevated at CpG dinucleotide sites owing to the mechanism of spontaneous deamination of 5-methylcytosine. This observation serves as the foundation for questions and models that we explore, namely:</p>

<ol>
  <li><em>How much variation in where, what type, and how frequent different types of mutations can be captured by sequence context?</em></li>
  <li><em>Can improved models for mutation rate variability help identify regions of functional constraint?</em></li>
  <li><em>How has the mutational process – measured by expanded windows of sequence context - changed over time?</em></li>
</ol>

<p>Below, I describe a couple of ideas of interest, but generally I am open to different types of analysis projects or ideas in this space!</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Further Development of Baymer</strong>. Our primary report for Baymer describes a ‘baseline’ implementation that is poised for further development. Some possible angles for novel development include (but not limited to):
    <ul>
      <li><em>Cross-substitution class modelling</em>. As currently implement, Baymer stratifies the data into 1-mer models (A&gt;G, A&gt;T, A&gt;C, etc.). It is possible that information about rates and local sequence context could be borrowed across all types.</li>
      <li><em>Multi-population models</em>. When we apply Baymer, we typically do so with by grouping individuals based on some notion of ancestry or similarlity to reference groups, but each separately. However, we know that the history of human populations is connected and can be described by phylogenetic trees with mutations shared across populations, private to specific branches, or may migrate across populations. Extensions to Baymer that consider such models could be imagined which fully utilize all data collectively (rather than stratifying) and could be used to make comparisons of rates across populations.</li>
      <li><em>Formal estimation of θ</em>. Baymer quantifies the <em>probability of mutation</em> for a given window of sequence context, based on the total number of mutated sites observed divided by the total number of k-mer sequence contexts in the reference (or reconstructed ancestral) genome. However, this basic model has limitations and assumptions which we acknowledge. First is that this probability depends on, but is not itself an estimate of the base pair per generation mutation rate, %mu;. It is also true that this probability depends on several additional quantities including (i) effective population size and other aspects of demographic history that influence patterns of genomic variation, (ii) forces that may influence patterns of variation locally, e.g., selection and recombination, (iii) biological or environmental factors that influence the mutation rate, either globally or locally. Thus, a direction for work would be to improve Baymer with explicit models of these forces to generate estimates of θ.</li>
      <li><em>Models for recurrent mutation events; mutation saturation</em>. Baymer makes an infinite sites model, but as the number of surveyed genomes increase, mutational contexts can become saturated. We also know that highly mutable sites that may not yet be saturated can be subjected to recurrent mutational events as well. Work to relax this assumption and accomodate these factors into a modified modeling procedure could be imagined.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Expanded model development for non-sequence context features</strong>. Other (non-sequence contexts) correlates of mutation rate - Replication timing, rate of recombination, strand-biases, functional genomics, etc. These factors absolutely contribute to variation in where, what type, and how frequent polymorphisms are observed and may (or may not) correlate with sequence context features. Another goal would be to select key factors and incorporate them into a unified Baymer model which describes variation across sequences context <em>and</em> one or more of these features.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Applications of Baymer - Across the Tree of Life</strong>. A central question is to what extent are mutational processes conserved across the tree of life. The reduction of cost for large scale sequencing has made creation of draft genomes of thousands of species now possible and facilitates the collection of population level variation data in those species. As a result, it is extremely timely to bring extant data - including but beyond mammals - to this basic question. Our lab is collaborating with the Mathieson Lab to cultivate &gt;100 species worth of polymorphism data to characterize mutational profiles across species, to determine if patterns of variation are different, differently evolving, and if we can correlate features common to species with mutational profiles or spectra, given the structure of the phylogenetic tree.</p>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Applications of Baymer - Coding Genome</strong>. Previous work focused on the non-coding genome; we expect that patterns of variation in the coding genome (incorporating codon context with sequence context window) should reflect what is observed in the non-coding genome, albeit reduced as a function of purifying selection. The approach would be to improve Baymer to be knowledgable about codon context and strand bias (directionality) to evaluate this model. In particular, the field uses synonymous mutation to generate an expectation for neutral (background) variation. Yet, a small fraction of these sites might still be subject to constraint (e.g., cryptic splice enhancer/modifiers). Thus, the ability to generate an appropriate background based on the genome background would facilitate better models to test all types of variation. Moreover, we also have substantially larger and better refined information on protein structure than ever before – generated empirically from Cryo-EM or through computational predictions e.g., <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-021-03819-2">AlphaFold</a>, AlphaFold2. Another objective is to better isolate regions in proteins likely to be the most constrained overall, to discover regions that are functionally important.</li>
</ol>

<div class="button-wrapper">
    <a class="button" href="/2024/01/11/Projects-Pop-Gen" data-style="" aria-label="button">
      
      
        <span>Back to Top</span>
      
    </a>
  </div>

<!-- section break -->
<!--
  background: ;
  dark: ;
  size: ;
-->

<p><a id="Selection"></a></p>

<h2 id="inference-of-selection">Inference of Selection</h2>

<p>I have a longstanding interest in discovery of genomic loci that may be targetted by directional positive selection or adaptive evolution in human populations. Ultimately, our goals are to built new and improve upon existing method to identify genomic signatures in data consistent with the action of different types of selection. I am also fond of much harder work to identify and characterize genes subject to selection that may arise from these efforts, connecting them to human traits to try to understand what may have been important in evolutionary history, primarily in human populations. Previous students in the lab developed new summary statistics to detect the action of balancing selection at genomic loci (the β-Statistics), or improved upon and applied existing tools (the iHS) to multi-population genetics data. More recently, I am interested in applying our work to model mutation rate variation as a function of sequence context to improve resolution of sequences - coding and non-coding - subject to purifying selection, and the strength of that selection on those sequences.</p>

<p>Some current interest include:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Applying Baymer and context models for new measures of functional constraint, extended regions of homozygosity, adaptation</strong>. The outputs from Baymer include the probability to observe polymorphism at a given nucleotide sites from population data. Using this information, it is possible to generate statistics that quantify the difference between observed vs. expected levels of polymorphism in specific genomic regions relative to the genome background as a whole. For example, we expect to see a reduction of polymorphic sites the coding relative to the non-coding genome, owing to functional constraint on coding sequences. Or, for example, directional selective sweeps that have have only recently fixed in a population will not have had much time to generate new mutations in the region; thus, one expects under some models to observe a deficit/absence of segregating sites in a ‘completed’ sweep (e.g., SLC24A5 in Europeans). Thus, projects include developing new test statistics based on this output to look for patterns in genomes consistent with different modes of selection.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Baymer - reinterpret previously pop-gen statistics with better models for mutation rates</strong>. Many of the population genetic summary statistics that I grew up learning about that were relevant for detection of selection - the MK test, HKA, dn/ds, etc. are based fundamentally on models for the mutational process. Generally, those models make limited assumptions about sequence context; these could be re-evaluated generally in the light of empirical data and evidence supporting variation in context-based mutability (within and across species).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Application of selection scans to multi-species data</strong>. In the process of assembling multi-species data for mutation-rate inference using Baymer, depending on the quality of the genome assembly and the data collected, it may be possible to apply some of our methods to species beyond humans, to identify signatures of selection from these data.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<div class="button-wrapper">
    <a class="button" href="/2024/01/11/Projects-Pop-Gen" data-style="" aria-label="button">
      
      
        <span>Back to Top</span>
      
    </a>
  </div>

<!-- section break -->
<!--
  background: ;
  dark: ;
  size: ;
-->

<p><a id="Interface"></a></p>

<h2 id="projects-at-the-interface-between-population-genomics-and-complex-trait-genetics">Projects at the Interface between Population Genomics and Complex Trait Genetics</h2>

<p>My previous training spans population genetic and complex disease trait mapping. I view these as complementary; population genetic thinking is quite informative (infectious, even) to interpreting complex trait association data, deciphering the genetic architecture of complex traits. Along these lines, we try to borrow ideas from population genetic models to understand disease-relevant variation or prediction problems, or how to develop and improve upon statistical genetics approaches that take advantage of multi-ancestry studies across human populations. My lab is always on the hunt for interesting angles where ideas from both spaces can be blended into interesting project. Some examples are listed below:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Somatic mutational data in cancer</strong>. The process and accumulation of somatic mutations is integral to the development of cancer in various tissues, and a great deal of prior work has been performed to learn about mutational signatures that are observed from these data as well as attempting to connect those signatures to molecular processes. However, most of these models are in 3-mer context models. Large-scale somatic mutational data are available to which Baymer could easily be applied to discover new signatures from data, or to use outputs from Baymer (and other measure of selection/constraint) to clarify somatic mutations that may be pathogenic.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Functional constraint models to interpret coding, non-coding variation for complex traits</strong>. While a great deal of functional constraint is observed and relatively well-quantified in the coding genome, quantification of constraint in the non-coding genome is much less obvious. There is a great deal of new methods and new data work from multi-species (mammalian) data, e.g., primate sequencing, Zoonomia, that is bringing unprecedent data and resolution to infer functional constraint. We think potentially there are gains to be made applying functional constraint inferred from measurements informed by sequence-context mutational probabilities inferred by Baymer to quantify constraint further. This could then be applied to interpret human complex trait association data, particularly as output from statistical signal fine-mapping, where additional information about variants within a credible set are likely to be causal would be exceedingly valuable to help guide functional follow-up experimental efforts.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Population Structure, admixture and quantitative genetics</strong>. We are engaged in large-scale DNA biobanks like the Million Veteran Program, of whom the participants are population genetically diverse. This provides the opportunity to better understand the population genetics of individuals from those biobanks, to infer and quantify admixture to improve genetic mapping effort, and to understand complex disease architecture better. In addition, inferring community-level information about sub-population structure can be very important to identifying pathogenic variation that is at elevated frequency in those groups.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<div class="button-wrapper">
    <a class="button" href="/2024/01/11/Projects-Pop-Gen" data-style="" aria-label="button">
      
      
        <span>Back to Top</span>
      
    </a>
  </div>]]></content><author><name>Ben Voight</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Links to Pubs: Pop Gen Mutation Rate Selection Baymer Demography]]></summary></entry></feed>